Guide to the Charles Augustus Russell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charles Augustus Russell papers
1928-1954
MS 837
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
Correspondence, memoranda, reports and miscellanea of Charles A. Russell. Professional material from public welfare, education, and international cultural cooperative organizations including the Edward W. Hazen Foundation are present.
Russell, Charles Augustus, 1886-1962
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and other printed matter from a number of philanthropic and public service organizations in which Charles Augustus Russell was active constitute these papers. The correspondence deals only with business matters of the various organizations; there are no family or personal letters. Materials other than correspondence, including memoranda written by or to Russell, are filed under the organization concerned.
From 1929 to 1949 Russell was president and treasurer of the Edward W. Hazen Foundation, an organization dedicated to promoting the public welfare, especially with regard to young people, education, religion in higher education, and international cultural cooperation. Papers of the Foundation from this period include legal and financial papers, statements of purpose, reports and memoranda. While chairman of the board in 1951, Russell worked with Gerhard W. Ditz on an investigation of employer-employee relations in the coal-mining industry; papers from this project include memoranda, proposals, questionnaires, and Ditz's notes and travel documents. There is also an earlier report on coal mining by Russell (1949). During the same period Russell was a member of the National Social Welfare Assembly and chairman of its National Budget Committee. Memoranda, reports, newsletters, budgets, and other related materials of this organization for coordinating and helping fund national and local social welfare agencies make up about half of the collection. There are, in addition, a few items from several other organizations with which Russell was connected, a small amount of biographical material, and miscellaneous papers not visibly related to the various organizations.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Augustus Russell was born in Essex, Connecticut on March 20, 1886. He was educated at Wesleyan University, where he received a B.A. in 1905. He was admitted to the New York bar in 1907 and practiced law in Connecticut between 1910 and 1914. He then served as attorney for the Connecticut Public Utilities Commission, a position he held until 1917. Between 1929 and 1949, he was president and treasurer of the Edward Hazen Foundation. Russell was active in many philanthropic and public service organizations. He died in 1962.
Child welfare; Coal mines and mining; International cooperation; Public welfare; Russell, Charles Augustus, 1886-1962; American Social Hygiene Association; Edward W. Hazen Foundation, Inc., New Haven (Conn.); National Recreation Association; National Social Welfare Assembly; United Defense Fund
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1930-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 8)
  - American Social Hygiene Association, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Edward W. Hazen Foundation
    - General, 1928-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 10 - 14)
    - Coal miner project, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 15 - 21)
  - National Social Welfare Assembly: general, 1946-1953 (Box 2, Folder 22 - 36)
  - National Budget Committee
    - General, 1946-1953 (Box 2, Folder 37 - 42)
    - Panel #1, 1952 March 24-25 (Box 3, Folder 43 - 44)
    - Panel #7, 1953 March 25-27 (Box 3, Folder 45 - 47)
  - National Recreation Association, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - United Community Defense Services Program, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - United Defense Fund, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 50 - 51)
  - Biographical materials, 1934, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-1941, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)